Now we restructured our actions in the last lecture,
imdi son dersimizdeki hareketlerimizi yeniden yaplandrdk.
now I want to dive into what we actually put into the action creators.
imdi, gerekte eylem yaratclarna attmz eylere dalmak istiyorum.
It's obviously easy for asynchronous code,
Akas ezamansz kod iin kolaydr.
the only place where we can execute asynchronous code is in our action creator,
Ezamansz kod yrtebildiimiz tek yer, ection yaratcmzdr.
it's what redux-thunk is made for and it's the common and best practice pattern if
Redux funk iin yapld ve yaygn ve en iyi uygulama ekli.
you need to reach out to a server to fetch data from it and thereafter store it in your store,
Bir sunucudan veri getirip daha sonra maazanzda depolamak iin bir sunucuya ulamanz gerekir.
definitely do that with the action creator. Send your HTTP request here instead of set timeout and once
Kesinlikle bunu eylem yaratcs ile yerine zaman am yerine HTP isteinizi gnderin ve cevap
the answer is there, the response is there,
bir kez yant orada duruyor.
store it in your store, you will see this in action in the course project of course.
Maazanzda saklayn, elbette ders projesinde bir eylem olarak greceksiniz.
However you can of course put much more logic into your action creators, think about saveResult,
Bununla birlikte, elbette eylem yaratclarnza daha fazla mantk koyabilir ve ayn sonucu dnebilirsiniz.
we save our result there, we get it as an argument and we simply return an action where we pass it on
Sonularm burada kurtarrz, onu bir argman olarak alrz ve basite bir yk olarak aktardmz bir
as a payload.
ilemi geri getiririz.
Now this is a very dry action creator,
imdi bu ok kuru bir ection yaratcs.
it doesn't do anything else but just return object with the unchanged response,
Baka bir ey yapmaz, ancak nesneyi yalnzca deimeden yantla dndrr.
result, excuse me.
Sonu bana bala.
Now obviously what we could do is we could create a constant maybe name it updatedResult and set it
ey, gncellenen sonucu ve sonu olarak iki kez eit olan bir sabit belki ad oluturabileceimizdir.
equal to result times two.
imdi elbette ki yapabileceimiz
Now obviously, that doesn't make this much sense here but we can theoretically alter anything you want
imdi aktr ki bu bu kadar mantkl deil, ancak burada istediinizi teorik olarak deitirebiliriz
here and you might have transformations which make more sense,
ve daha anlaml hale gelen dnmlere sahip olabilirsiniz.
maybe we want to update some id, we want to add a user name and we then pass on our updatedResult.
Belki bir kullanc ad eklemek istediimiz baz fikirleri gncellemek istiyoruz ve daha sonra gncellenmi sonucumuzu iletiyoruz.
The thing is this happens upon saving the result,
Asl olan bu, yllarca tasarruf ettikten sonra olur.
keep that in mind,
Aklmda tutarm.
our application still works. If I store that, we stored 20 because we updated the result by multiplying
Uygulamamz hala sakladmz bir maaza iin geerli nk saldrlarn ikiyle
it with two.
arplarak gncelledik.
Now we have logic in the action creator
imdi, eylem yaratannda mantk var.
and this might be valid logic instead of some nonsense operation like this one,
Ve bu, bunun gibi mantksz bir ilem yerine geerli mantk olabilir.
the thing is you could of course also execute the same logic
Elbette, ayn mant da yrtebilecein bir ey var.
so let me revert this to the previous state of just passing on response.
O halde bunu yantlamaya balamamn bir nceki durumuyla deitirmeme izin verin.
You could execute that same logic if you need to transform the data before storing it in the state which
Verileri, olabilecek en iyi durumda depolamadan nce deitirmeniz gerekiyorsa,
is perfectly fine which might happen.
ayn mant da uygulayabilirsiniz.
You can execute that same logic of course in your reducer, here
Ayn mant redktrnzde buradan da uygulayabilirsiniz.
storeResult,
Sonu sakla.
here we concatenate the result and store the value and
Burada sonucu birletirip deeri depolarz.
now obviously, nothing is keeping us from multiplying this with two here,
imdi akas hibir ey bizi ikili ile arpmamz salyor.
if I do it there in the result reducer,
Onlarla saldr redksiyoncusu yaparsam.
now if I save 10, we still store 20 in the store as you can see
imdi 10 tasarruf ederseniz, grdnz gibi 20 maazasnda hala depolarz.
but now we change it at a totally different place,
Ama imdi bunu tamamen farkl bir yerde deitiriyoruz.
we change it in the reducer.
Redktrde deitiriyoruz.
Now as I said, this operation here might not make that much sense but you'll often have cases where you
imdi burada sylediim gibi bu ilem mantkl olmayabilir, ancak devlette depolamadan nce gerekten bir
really want to change something before you store it in the state,
eyi deitirmek istediiniz vakalara sk sk sahip olacaksnz.
you'll not always get the value you just want to pass on,
Gemek istediiniz deeri her zaman elde edemezsiniz.
where should you then change it? In the reducer
Nerede Denne'yi indirgeyicide deitirmelisin.
as I show you here, you can of course also run some code before returning here, change data or in the action
Burada gsterdiim gibi, deiim verilerinizi veya herhangi bir eylem yaratcsn iade etmeden nce elbette baz kod
creator
da altrabilirsiniz.
like I showed you before, here what I commented out.
Sana daha nce burada akladm eyi gsterdim sanki.
Both works,
Her iki eser de.
what's better? Let's take a closer look.
Daha yakndan bakmak daha iyi olur.
In the end, the question comes down to where to put the logic,
Nihayetinde soru, mant nereye koyacaklarna inanyor.
we have action creators and reducers as options. Now
Gerek yaratclar ve reticilerimiz u an seenek olarak var.
action creators as you learned are great for running async code when you dispatch an action, reducers
rendiiniz gibi eylem yaratclar, bir eylem gnderirken uyuturucu kodu altrmak iin
on the other hand only are able to run synchronous code and are pure, input in updated state out. Reducers
harika Yaverland zerindeki kstlayclar yalnzca senkron kod altrabiliyor ve gncellenmi durum azaltma redktrlerinde
however keep that in mind, are meant to be the place where you update the state,
saf giri yapyor ancak bunu aklnzda tuttuunuz yerler, belirtmek, bildirmek.
this is one core redux concept. Action creators are not core redux concept, a core concept are actions,
Bu bir ekirdek redux kavramdr eylem yaratclar Natcore redux kavram ekirdek bir kavram bizim eylemlerimizdir.
these javascript objects with a type and a payload. So the reducer is the core concept and the whole idea
DS, redktrlerin ekirdek konsepti ve redux'un arkasndaki btn fikir, bir tr ve
behind redux is that the reducer is the only thing which updates the state, action creators shouldn't
yk olan kskan nesneleri kskantr; redktr, devlet eylemlerini gelitiren tek eyin ok fazla
prepare the state too much
sahnelemeye hazrlanmamas gerektiidir.
for that reason because it should be the reducer which does the update but there of course is also a difference
Bu nedenle, gncelleme yapan redktr olmal ama elbette ki durumun gncellenmesi
between updating the state which essentially just means returning a new object which makes up our
arasnda bir farkllk var ki bu sadece aslnda bizim durumumuzu oluturan ve devlete giren
state and changing the data which goes into the state.
verileri deitiren yeni bir nesnenin dndrlmesi anlamna geliyor.
Still you can find arguments for both directions,
Yine de her iki ynde de argmanlar bulabilirsiniz.
I lean towards putting the logic into the reducer and not too much logic into the action creator.
Mant redktre koymaya doru eiliyorum ve eylem yaratcs iin ok fazla mantk deil.
Asynchronous code has to go there but once you got back the data from the server you might need to reach
Ezamansz kod oraya gitmek zorunda, ancak sunucudaki verileri dndrdkten sonra
out, you can of course transform it in the action creator and you should do that to a certain extent
el uzatmanz gerekebilir, elbette bunu Oluturan eyleminde dntrebilirsiniz ve bunu belirli
but once you've got data that is relatively clean, you should hand it off to the reducer.
bir dzeye getirmelisiniz, ancak bir zamanlar nispeten temiz, reticiye teslim etmeniz lazm.
And if you then still need to manipulate it, for example by taking 8 times 2 or anything like that, in my
Ve yine de, rnein 8 kez veya bunun gibi bir ey dnerek maniple
opinion that should go into the reducer.
etmeye ihtiyacnz varsa Bence buna indirgeyici girmeliyiz.
Now you will also find arguments for the other side and in the end, it's your decision. If you choose
imdi de dier taraf iin argmanlar bulacaksnz ve buna ramen onu
one approach, stick to it though, don't change it,
deitirmeden bir sopa seerseniz bunun sonucudur.
don't put a lot of logic in one action creator, just to then have a lot of logic in another reducer.
Bir eylem yaratanna ok fazla mantk koymayn, yalnzca ok fazla mantk ve say azaltc yoktur.
Be consistent and decide, where do you want to transform and prepare your data, the action creator or reducer,
Tutarl olun ve nereye dnmek istediinize karar verin ve veri yn oluturan veya educe'unuzu
I recommend the latter
hazrlayn veya ikincisini neririm.
but ultimately it's up to you,
Ama sonuta sana kalm.
just take a consistent route.
Tutarl bir yol tutun.